Okay, welcome back to Garys Economics.
Today we are going to explain
why asset prices keep going up.
Okay, you were probably expecting
me to do a breakdown of the local election results,
but I've been in France all week promoting my book,
so you are getting this video, which I shot last week,
which is inspired by the pretty insane situation, which
you may or may not be aware of, which is that last week,
on both Monday the 27th and Tuesday 28th of April,
which are just a couple of days ago,
and I'm shooting now,
the US stock market hit a new all-time high.
And just sit with that for a second.
Not just the US stock market, the Japanese stock
market hit a new global all-time high today.
I'm shooting this on Wednesday morning, 29th.
And this,
I think is, for anyone who hasn't... didn't know this,
this is the first thing you need to know.
We're sitting here in the middle of,
like a war which,
has been focused on destroying the economy.
That is, you know, the basically Iranian sort
of primary plan is to, like, damage the global economy.
We are expecting to see, like,
a pretty significant collapse in living standards
all around the Western world.
Well, not just the Western world, the entire world.
And yet, despite this, like, collapse,
intentional destruction of the economy,
intentional collapsing of living standards, global stock
markets are, like, in many cases the highest
they've ever been, and it's not just Japan and the US.
Right?
So, you know, Japan and the US, all-time highs.
The Germany stock market is not even down on the year.
It's flat on the year.
The UK stock market, FTSE 100, is up 21% in a year.
I'll just go through them, yeah.
France up 11%, Australia is up 2%, Spain is up...
Can that be right?
Spain is up 32%, and, you know, these are, like,
one-year moves from a situation where even one year ago
most of these stock markets were at all-time highs.
It's not just the stock market.
The gold price, gold has gone absolutely mental.
Gold has gone up 98.5% in the last two years.
The silver price has gone up 174% in the last two years.
So we're sitting here, in the midst of, like,
an enormous economic crisis, and what we are seeing is,
like, all global asset prices, all global stock markets,
like, doing incredibly well.
And a lot of people are confused about this
because people have generally been led to believe,
and there is a general assumption,
that when the economy goes good, stock markets go up.
When stock
markets go up, it's because the economy is good.
When the economy is bad, stock markets go down.
If the stock markets go down, that means the economy is bad.
And yet here we are in the midst of, like,
probably the most obvious piece of economic, like,
****ness we've seen in a long time.
Stock market's going through the roof.
We are going to explain to you what is happening.
So the first thing to say is, like, this is not new.
So I'm talking to you now in 2026,
in the midst of one economic crisis
that appears to be pushing stock markets up,
and obviously five years ago, we had COVID,
which was another enormous economic crisis, and
what was the long-term effect of COVID on asset prices?
Gold, stocks, housing, they all went up.
2011 sovereign debt crisis pushed asset prices up,
and 2008 the, obviously the, credit crisis,
the Lehman shock, the massive 2008 economic crisis,
in the long run pushed asset prices up.
So, you know, what is happening?
Why is it that we have this thing happening
which is, like, totally the opposite
of what is supposed to happen?
And why does it seem to be that
whenever there is an economic crisis, Iran war, COVID,
2008 crisis, why do they always push asset prices up
when we expect them to push asset prices down?
So a narrative was starting to form on this,
sort of like 10 years ago, which was that...
So 2008, for anyone who doesn't know,
I guess I'm getting older now 2008 was,
like, a massive credit crisis.
It turned out that basically, like, all of the banks,
at least in the Western world,
had lent money to people who couldn't pay it back.
The banks would have gone bankrupt.
The banks stopped lending.
Nobody could get a loan.
Governments had to, like, go in and bail them out.
There's a massive collapse in the economy and
in living standards, a massive spike in unemployment.
It's generally accepted
that this was bad for the economy.
After that, 3 years later,
we had the 2011 sovereign debt crisis, which was
a crisis where basically primarily European governments
found that traders and economists thought that
they couldn't pay their debts back, and the governments
in many cases were forced to do austerity.
The UK was already doing austerity, but most obviously
Greece was forced to do enormous public spending cuts.
This was also bad for the economy.
So it was generally accepted
that these crises were bad for the economy.
But a narrative started to form about
why they pushed asset prices up, which was quite simple,
which was that these crises caused interest rates
to be pushed down.
So some context on interest rates.
Interest rates, which is the amount that you pay
to borrow money, the amount you get for lending money.
Before 2008, before the Lehman crisis,
they were at levels generally in the West
which are similar to where they are now, sort of 4%, 5%,
maybe a little bit higher than they are now.
And,
when 2008 happened, the main sort of systemic response,
the main response by governments and central banks,
the institutions who are supposed to manage your economy,
was to aggressively slash interest rates
to effectively 0%.
This happened in 2008.
It also happened during COVID.
So you see
this massive reduction in interest rates to 0%.
And this, it was generally came to be accepted
that the reason that asset prices did well
in the long run after the 2008 Lehman crisis,
despite the economy being weak, was that interest
rates were massively, massively reduced.
Now, sort of in economic theory,
there's supposed to be, like, quite a tight relationship
between interest rates and asset prices.
And I'll explain why, right?
So when you look at an investment,
the most simple investment you can make
is to, say, put your money in a savings account.
Because you know you put it in there
and the bank's going to say,
like, "We're going to give you 5% a year." So say that you,
you put a million pound in a savings account
at 5% a year, you are going to get your 5% a year,
which is £50,000 a year.
Now, let's assume you're also looking
at an alternative investment, which is you want to buy a
buy-to-let property, and you've found yourself, like,
a nice big house, big luxury house
that you can rent out for £50,000 a year.
And you're thinking, "Okay, well,
how much should I pay for it?" Well, you know
that if you put one million pounds into a bank account,
you're going to get £50,000 a year,
which is the same return as this rental property.
So you would imagine,
since both of these investments yield a similar return
of £50,000 pounds a year, this house should also be worth
maybe something close to one million pounds.
Now, that's a simplified example,
but it makes sense, right?
If interest rates are 5%,
then a house that gives $50,000 a year rent
should be roughly equivalent to a bank account
that gives £50,000 a year interest in rent.
Okay, so this house should
be worth about one million pounds if rates are about 5%.
Now let's assume rates are much lower, 1%.
Now, if I put my one million pounds in a bank account,
I'm only going to get £10,000 a year.
Poor me.
Now, let's assume that the same house is on the market,
and it's still able
to get something like £50,000 rent.
In this example, would
I be willing to pay a million pounds for this house?
Well, a million pound is only going to get me £10,000
in a bank account now.
So in order to get £50,000,
the amount I would have to put in a bank account
to get £50,000 now is going to be 5 times bigger,
so this is equivalent to 5 million pounds.
So in theory, and again, this a very simplified example,
if interest rates are 5%, then a £50,000 a year
rent, rental house should be worth about one million.
But if interest rates are 1%,
that same £50,000 a year house
should be worth about 5 million, which is enormous.
It's 5 times bigger.
So I think what this shows you,
it just basically...
And again, this is a very simplified example.
This shows you that, in theory, interest rate
reductions, especially big interest rate reductions,
should have, in theory, the power to push asset prices,
especially assets that have a return,
like housing or like profitable stocks, up really a lot.
Okay, this is very simplified,
but I'm trying to give you the basic understanding
that interest rates, in economic theory,
really aggressively affect the price of assets.
Because if interest rates fall a lot from 5% to 1%,
then I can't get any interest on my money anymore.
So suddenly,
other assets, assets that give, like, real returns,
like rental property or like a profitable company,
a share in a profitable company,
suddenly they are worth so much more relative to money.
So this was basically the theory which explained
why is it that in that period after 2008,
that the economy was really incredibly weak
for, well, I mean, you could argue 18 years,
because it's still weak now.
But let's say that the 10 years following 2008,
the reason, the reason that was sort of given
as to why stock markets did so well
despite the economy being so weak
was very simply interest rates are incredibly low,
so nobody wants to have money in a savings account.
Everybody wants to hold real assets instead,
because they give you much more return.
Okay, so that, that's your story, right?
That's your sort of simple story.
Blah, blah, blah.
This is why.
That's your sort of simple story.
That this is why asset prices did well after 2008.
But then this crazy thing happened, right, which was
we had COVID, and initially, COVID also caused interest
rates to fall, although in many cases, interest
rates were already 0% even before COVID.
But interest rates did fall further where they could
during COVID, and the asset prices, similarly to 2008,
they fell initially and then they went up.
But then after COVID,
this, like, really crazy thing happened,
which was suddenly inflation spiked
and interest rates increased very, very quickly.
So interest rates before COVID were sort of,
depending on what interest rate
you're looking at, you know, base rate's close to 0%,
longer term interest rates may be 1%, 1.5%.
Very quickly, you're seeing base rates go up to 5%,
and long-term interest rates go up to, like, 5%
or maybe more in many cases.
So in COVID,
what we then had was severe economic weakness
combined with aggressively rising interest rates.
So surely now asset prices are going to fall.
But what actually happened after COVID,
again, asset prices rose really quickly.
So this is, like, even crazier
and I think really perhaps raising some questions
about the correctness of the previous narrative.
Like, if the idea was the reason that asset prices
did so well after the, like, economic crisis of 2008
and the economic malaise of the 2010s
was because interest rates fell so much, then wh-
that does not explain at all why asset
prices did so well after COVID when the economy was weak
and living standards were weak,
and also as interest rates rose significantly.
And we're seeing the same thing now basically
in the Iran war, which is the Iran war, obviously
we're like in the midst of it here and now, I think
it is pretty certain it's going to be bad for the economy,
bad for living standards.
Interest rates have risen, not enormously but like
pretty significantly since the beginning of the war,
because inflation is going to rise
and central banks are going to rise base rates.
And yet once again, we are seeing the
repetition of this like COVID dynamic of interest
rates are going up, the economy is going down, living
standards are falling, and yet asset
prices are not falling and maybe even increasing.
Like, what's causing that?
So I am going to put forward an argument
as to what has been really causing
the aggressive increases in asset prices
throughout the world, in the last 18 years,
but especially during the last 5 or 6 years since COVID.
And I will to sort of support my argument
add that I have consistently correctly predicted
that these asset prices would rise.
So I...
If you can watch the first video on this channel
that I did in 2020
at the very beginning of COVID predicting
it would cause a massive increase in asset prices.
I did a video about two years ago,
two and a half years ago, predicting
that we would see further aggressive increases in asset
prices even though interest rates were high and rising,
and I made tons of money on these predictions.
So I'd like to think that, you know,
I have a little bit of a right to speak on these things.
In my opinion, what has been under-discussed
and under-understood as a driver of these asset prices
is deficits and distribution.
So in a sense here, I'm repeating an argument
that I made at the beginning of COVID,
which is when the government runs a deficit,
or in essence really anybody runs a deficit,
somebody accumulates money, and this is
basically an intrinsic part of our monetary system.
But the way it basically works is like this,
you know, if I borrow a ton of money
and then give that money away,
somebody has to have more money now quite simply.
And I think this is something
which is unfortunately not well understood,
and it's one of the reasons why we are in this mess.
So I think the clearest sort of way to understand
this is to look at COVID itself, because I think
it's just such a clear example of this happening,
which is at the very beginning of COVID,
we knew that
governments were going to run very long-term lockdowns,
we knew that governments were going to have
to subsidise people's wages, and we knew that
the way that governments were going to fund
that was to essentially borrow or in some cases print,
we can argue the details, borrow or print
an enormous amount of money and give that money out.
And I'm not necessarily opposed
to that policy, but it's important to recognise that
when governments do this,
when governments run very big deficits,
some group of society must accumulate money.
And when the deficit is enormously big,
and the deficits in COVID
were just like mind-blowingly big.
In the UK it was like £20,000 per adult.
I think in the US it was like something more like,
like 40 or $40,000 per adult.
Crazily huge amounts of money.
When the government runs enormous, enormous deficits,
somebody accumulates money.
And I did all this analysis at the beginning of COVID,
because my background is like distribution
and inequality.
All I really wanted to know at the beginning
of COVID was, "Who is it going to be that accumulates,
that is on the other side of this enormous deficit
that will be run by the government?"
And if you want to see like the details of that,
you can go and watch the first video on this channel.
You can see me following it through.
But I'll give you the, the conclusion.
The conclusion I came to
was that these enormous government deficits in COVID
were going to end up being accumulated
basically by the richest people in the country.
And that happened here in the UK, but it also happened
pretty much wherever you're watching,
unless you're watching from Switzerland.
That happened in basically every single country
in the world.
And that led me to be able to make these like,
really in my opinion, like quite obvious conclusions.
Like if we know that what is going to happen
is governments are going to run huge deficits,
and the richest people in the world are going to start
accumulating like unbelievably enormous piles of cash,
like what is the obvious consequence of that?
The most obvious consequence if
you give like rich people an enormous amount of money...
So this is something you need to understand.
When I talk about rich people,
especially you're talking like very rich people,
people with like 10, 20, 100 million pounds
or, you know, billions of dollars.
If you give a large amount of money
to somebody with that amount of wealth,
they by and large will not spend much of it.
They won't increase their spending much.
Very rich people are not very cash constrained.
They can already
sort of buy the things they want in most cases.
If you give them an enormous amount of money,
what are they going to do?
They're going to buy assets.
It's the most obvious thing they're going to do.
They are going to buy assets.
Like, if somebody gives me now £100,000,
I will buy that day £100,000 worth of assets.
That is what rich people do with their money.
So I think really, to be honest,
like this really quite simply answers the question
because the way that we dealt with COVID
is in many ways the same way that
we dealt with the 2008 financial crisis,
the 2011 sovereign debt crisis in Europe,
and the same way we're dealing with the Iran crisis now.
Which is we tried
to fix it by the government running an enormous deficit,
leading to an accumulation of an enormous amount of cash
with richer people, which they use to buy assets.
We really have a, like, a established playbook now,
which we can see happens again and again and again and
again every time there's a crisis, which is the way that
we resolve this is the government borrows a ton of money
from the rich and gives that money back to the rich,
and uses that massive redistribution of wealth
to basically resolve the crisis.
Which means that every single crisis ends up
with an enormous amount of money
piling up with the rich.
Massive increase in inequality,
massive increase in wealth and power of the rich.
And the most obvious consequence
of that is an increase in asset prices.
And I think in COVID,
what happened was the amount of money given to the rich
was so much that it increased the consumption
and actually pushed up inflation, which meant
that we saw this interesting combination of asset prices
going up and interest rates going up at the same time.
And you know...
A lot of people were really confused
about that when it was happening.
But the reason I was able to predict
it was because that is exactly what you would expect
if you just understand that
rich people have been given an enormous amount of money,
an enormous amount of money.
The first thing that's going to happen
is asset prices will rise, and the second thing is
if it is sufficiently large amount of money, that
it even increases their consumption, inflation will go
up with it, which means interest rates will go up, too.
And that is how we were able to see
this really interesting combination of movements,
which is asset prices going up, you know,
gold and stocks going up at the same time.
These things are supposed
to move in opposite directions.
And interest rates going up at the same time,
which is supposed to push asset prices down.
None of these movements when
viewed by themselves make sense until you recognise what
we are doing is transferring enormous amounts of money,
enormous amounts of cash
to the richest people in the world.
And what are they going to do with that?
They're going to increase their purchases of assets,
and if the money's enough,
they're going to increase their spending,
which is going to drive up inflation
and interest rates as well.
Okay, so how do you react to this?
Okay, first thing to say is you need to recognise
that asset prices going up is not good for you.
Unless you are a very rich person, asset prices going up
is not good for you.
It is not good for workers.
It is not good for ordinary people.
Expensive assets mean, in the first instance,
you cannot afford to buy a house, your kids can't afford
to buy a house, and you can't afford to buy a pension.
It basically means
you are being squeezed out of asset ownership.
You are being squeezed out of financial stability.
In particular, if the reason that asset
prices are going up is because your governments
are giving enormous amounts of cash to the rich, then
this is going to increasingly push governments
into very weak financial positions.
You're seeing this very clearly
in the situation of the UK, but it's also happening
in places like Italy, places like Greece,
even places like the US are going in this direction.
If you keep moving in this direction, where every time
you have a crisis, we deal with it by the governments
giving a huge amount of money to the rich,
you will all end up in situations
where we are increasingly seeing the UK government in,
where basically they cannot borrow any more money
because
financial markets will not lend them any more money.
And then you reach situations
where suddenly you have crises like these now,
and governments are increasingly powerless
to defend the population from the economic consequences
of things that are happening.
The second thing is I think you need to stop
associating high asset prices with a strong economy.
This idea has, like, been in the public consciousness
for a long time, but I think it should be by now
incredibly clear from the last 20 years
that weak economies can, and in fact
very often do, create incredibly expensive assets.
And I think in particular, we need to be able to
start recognising a particular form of economic crisis,
which I think is becoming, like,
the most common and normal form of economic crisis,
which is an economic crisis which is
primarily being driven by an increase in inequality.
And when you have this increase in inequality,
you see this combination of things,
which is weakening living standards,
increasing asset prices, increasing inequality.
You need to start recognising
that these increasing asset prices
are a symptom of the economic weakening.
Because you have this situation at the moment where
you see Donald Trump says it explicitly, says, "Oh,
you know, but look, the stock market is doing well."
I think you need to recognise that high house prices,
high asset prices, high stock prices,
high gold prices are a direct consequence of the kind of
extreme inequality that is driving you and your family
and ordinary families like yours into poverty.
Expensive assets are a consequence
of your falling living standards.
The third thing that I want to say, which I think
is actually really worth sitting and thinking about, and
I think is really, really interesting, which is if you look
at crises like 2008, if you look at crises like COVID,
and the Iran war is maybe, like, slightly different.
If an economic crisis can be resolved by governments
running a massive deficit and giving that deficit
to the rich and using that money to protect the living
standards of poor and ordinary people, then that crisis
could only ever have been a crisis of distribution.
I think this is a really,
really important thing to understand, right?
If the government is able to stop your living standards
from being hit by borrowing from the rich people
and getting the assets back from the rich people,
then that means the assets themselves had,
had never disappeared.
If production had really fallen in these situations
and productive capacity had really fallen,
then we wouldn't have been able to protect
your living standards by borrowing from the rich.
All borrowing from the rich
ever does is change the distribution. So if your living
standards can be protected by governments
managing the distribution, then the crisis
could only ever have been a crisis of distribution.
And I think once you start to recognise
that problems can be resolved by governments agreeing
to go into debt to the rich, then you should also
be able to recognise that these living standard problems
were being imposed by the rich.
You know, the government goes to the rich
and says, "Listen, don't crush living standards.
We will agree to go into debt to you." And
the rich says, "Okay, we won't crush living standards."
And living standards don't get crushed.
What that shows you, these are crises of distribution.
These are crises of distribution.
And I think when you understand that,
that can and should be like a really profound source
of positivity because what we often view as these, like,
almost crises of, like, sin, like our economy
is weak because we've managed it badly.
Our governments are in debt
because we've managed it badly.
If we recognise that the reason governments are in debt
is because they are trying
to fix crises of distribution, we can realise that
actually the resources are all still there.
Governments are going into debt because they are trying
to deal with growing problems of distribution.
And if
we are able to deal with those distributional problems
without consistently giving away government wealth
and without consistently the government going in debt
to the rich,
then these economic crises don't need to happen.
These economic crises don't need to exist.
If we deal with the distributional problem,
then living standards don't fall.
So I think once you recognise that,
then you can see that if we deal more seriously
with the taxation of the riches, any problem that can
be resolved by the government going in debt to the rich
can also be resolved without the increase in inequality
by the government taxing the rich.
It's as simple as that.
These are just 2 different ways
of managing the distribution of resources.
So I think once you really recognise the reason asset
prices are going up is because inequality is increasing,
the reason government debt is going up
is because inequality is increasing, the reason living
standards falling is because inequality is increasing,
then you recognise we can stop all of these things
if only we stop inequality from increasing.
Housing does not need to be unaffordable.
We do not need to see ordinary families struggling
to turn the heating on, struggling to feed their kids.
You know, this was not normal 70 years ago,
and it is normal now because we increased inequality,
and we can make it rare again now
if we stop increasing that inequality.
So I think when I look at rising asset prices,
what I really see is, like, the canary in the coal mine,
which is what this shows us is
that the rich are getting richer and richer and richer
and richer, and that's being subsidised by governments
going more and more and more and more into debt
in a way that is not long-term sustainable.
But it also shows us the potential solution,
which is we can stop these things from developing
if only we create a tax system which taxes rich people
more fairly, which taxes wealth more
and taxes work less, which stops creating a situation
where billionaires pay lower tax than their cleaners,
where billionaires pay lower tax than you.
So what I think is this is fixable.
This is 100% fixable.
People ask me,
because I've done this video about asset prices, like,
will... Do I think asset prices will keep going up?
I've been betting on it for a long time.
They've gone up so much, there's obviously a chance
of, like, big reversals in the short term.
Prices are incredibly volatile right now.
But the fact is we are still dealing
with these economic problems in such a way
that every time there's a crisis, including the crisis
we're having right now, what happens?
Government deficits increase
and the rich accumulate money, and that is absurd.
You know, 18 years after 2008,
we should not still be dealing with crises in such a way
as we massively transfer resources from governments,
from welfare states to the rich.
Listen, if you want economies which are stable
and provide stable living conditions, you cannot
accept continually increasing inequality, and the way to
do that is to fight with us to tax wealth, not work.
So thanks very much.
Send this video to your mum.
Tell your friends, tell your family. We're winning.
We're going to win.
Good luck.
Thank you.